<?xml version='1.0' ?>
  
<checklist version='0.1' name="fedoraus" revision="0.1">
  <category name='Security'>
    <description>Security Concerns</description>
    <entry name='Canonical Source'>
      <display default='true'/>
      <states>
        <state name='Pass'>
          <output>Source URL %s is canonical</output>
        </state>
        <state name='Fail'>
          <output>Source URL wrong; %s is the canonical URL</output>
        </state>
      </states>
      <description>You should check to be sure the Source line contains a valid URL.
        This helps ensure that the person creating the RPM is not downloading
        a trojan source tarball from an unknown entity.</description>
      <input>Source URL</input>
    </entry>
    <entry name='MD5Sum verified'>
      <display default='true'/>
      <states>
        <state name='Pass'>
          <output>Upstream MD5Sum verified</output>
        </state>
        <state name='Fail'>
          <output>Upstream MD5Sum does not match!</output>
        </state>
      </states>
      <description>You should always verify that the upstream source matches the
        source provided in the SRPM.  One method of doing this is to download
        the pristine source from a known canonical web site and take the MD5
        hash of it with md5sum.  Comparing this hash to the hash of the
        source in the SRPM should be identical.</description>
    </entry>
    <entry name='Upstream GPG Checked'>
      <display default='false'/>
      <states>
        <state name='Pass'>
          <output>Good upstream GPG Signature: %s</output>
        </state>
        <state name='Fail'>
          <output>Upstream GPG Signatures do not match: %s</output>
        </state>
        <state name='Not-Applicable'>
          <output>No upstream GPG</output>
        </state>
      </states>
      <description>Whenever possible, you should check that the upstream tarball is
        truly from a trusted source.  One method of doing this is to have the
        upstream developers sign the release tarball with their gpg keys.
        Another, related method is for the upstream developer gpg sign a
        file with MD5sums of the source tarballs.  If the upstream developer
        uses either of these methods, please be sure to verify the source by
        checking the valdity of the gpg signatures.</description>
      <input>GPG output</input>
    </entry>
  </category>
  <category name="Spec">
    <description>Potential spec file problems</description>
    <entry name="BuildRoot">
      <display default='false'/>
      <states>
        <state name='Pass'>
          <output>Buildroot has all required elements</output>
        </state>
        <state name='Fail'>
          <output>Buildroot lacks certain elements</output>
        </state>
      </states>
      <description>The spec file's BuildRoot: must contain %{_tmppath} in as a prefix
        so the local user can define where packages are temporarily installed.
        It should also contain a unique identifier to prevent collisions
        should multiple users be creating packages.  The Fedora suggested
        BuildRoot is:
        %{_tmppath}/%{name}-%{version}-%{release}-root-%(%{__id_u} -n)</description>
    </entry>
  </category>
</checklist>
